MATTIA GIANOTTI

07/11/1992

POLITECNICO DI MILANO mattia.gianotti@polimi.it

3490536079

Linkedin

LANGUAGES





I am Mattia Gianotti, a Research Fellow at Politecnico di Milano (i3Lab: https://i3lab. polimi.it/). I have completed my Ph.D. and have become an expert in Interactive Smart Spaces and Multi-Sensory Environments. Since obtaining my Master's degree, I have passionately dedicated myself to applying technology for the well-being of others in various ways, particularly utilizing IoT technologies.

Please find below the links to websites showcasing my best projects:

https://ludomi.polimi.it/en/ludomi-welcome/

https://5a.polimi.it/

WORK EXPERIENCE

25/05/2017 - 04/08/2017

CONSULTANT @BLUE REPLY

Development of Web Portals with IBM technology (Websphere portal e Web Content manager)

01/01/2020 - PRESENT

RESEARCH FELLOW @DEIB

INNOVATIVE INTERACTIVE INTERFACE LABORATORY (I3LAB) – DEPARTMENT OF ELECTRONIC, INFORMATION AND BIOENGINEERING (DEIB) AT POLITECNICO DI MILANO

I am a Research Fellow at I3Lab (https://i3lab.polimi.it/) under the supervision of Prof. Franca Garzotto. Throughout my tenure, I have been involved in various national (LUDOMI, Next Generation UPP) and international research projects, assuming leadership roles in several of them. These include work package leadership in international projects such as INCLUDE, Sara ++, and PLET, as well as work package and task leadership in national projects such as 5A and ACTIVE3.

Additionally, I have contributed to the field through the publication of 20 research papers in esteemed international conferences and journals. Sharing my knowledge, I have also served as a teaching assistant, imparting expertise in Internet of Things, Smart spaces, Virtual Reality, Augmented Reality, and Conversational Agents technologies to Master Degree students across various curriculums.

01/09/2022 - PRESENT

ADJUNCT PROFESSOR @POLITECNICO DI MILANO

As an Adjunct Professor at Politecnico di Milano, I have had the privilege of contributing to the academic community and fostering the growth of students.

During my tenure, I have developed and taught courses of Laboratorio di Computer Grafica – Modulo Informatica Applicata in Bachelor program for Design school, covering topics such as the creation and management of online videogames using Phaser3 framework and 3D rendering technology to create a narrative involving artifacts to communicate social themes such as UN SDGs. Through innovative teaching methods and hands-on projects. I have encouraged critical thinking, problem-solving, and practical application of theoretical concepts.

Next Accademic Year I will have the opportunity to teach in the course of Final Design Studio -Technologies for Connected Products and Systems in the Master program for Digital and Interaction Design - Scuola del Design

EDUCATION AND TRAINING

BACHELOR DEGREE IN INGEGNERIA INFORMATICA 2010 - 2014

apolitecnico di milano

Score 93/110

MASTER DEGREE IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING -2014

INGEGNERIA INFORMATICA @POLITECNICO DI MILANO - 28/04/2017

Master Thesis title: Rehabilitation Games for Juvenile Rheumatic Disease to Knees and Ankles

Score: 107/110

01/09/2017 - 20/07/2021

PHD WITH HONORS (MULTISENSORY MULTIMODAL INTERACTION TECHNOLOGY AND DESIGN FOR PEOPLE WITH NDD)

@POLITECNICO DI MILANO, I3LAB

Joint Ph.D. program between Computer Science and Engineering and Design

The research explores emerging technologies and design methods for creating new IoT (Internet of Things)-enhanced multisensory interventions for individuals with Neurodevelopmental Disorders NDD). This interdisciplinary doctoral project combines Information Engineering and Design. Due to its inherent nature, this research requires an interdisciplinary approach at the intersection of ICT Engineering, Product Design, and Interaction Design. It involves a strong technological know-how, engineering methods, Design Thinking, and a Lean UX approach. https://i3lab.polimi.it/

P.h. D. Thesis title: Smart Multisensory Environments for Children with Neurodevelopmental Disorders

ABILITAZIONE ALLA PROFESSIONE DI INGEGNERE (ESAME DI STATO) 21/02/2022

apolitecnico di milano

PUBLICATIONS

2018

Gelsomini, M., Rotondaro, A., Cosentino, G., **Gianotti, M.**, Riccardi, F., & Garzotto, F. (2018, November). **On the effects of a nomadic multisensory solution for children's playful learning**. In Proceedings of the 2018 ACM International Conference on Interactive Surfaces and Spaces (pp. 189-201).

DOI: https://doi.org/10.1145/3279778.3279790

2019

Garzotto, F., Gelsomini, M., **Gianotti, M**., & Riccardi, F. (2019). **Engaging children with neurodevelopmental disorder through multisensory interactive experiences in a smart space**. Social Internet of Things, (pp. 167-184).

DOI: https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-94659-7 9

Cosentino, G., Leonardi, G., Gelsomini, M., Spitale, M., **Gianotti, M.**, Garzotto, F., & Arquilla, V. (2019, March). **GENIEL: an auto-generative intelligent interface to empower learning in a multi-sensory environment**. In Proceedings of the 24th ACM International Conference on Intelligent User Interfaces (IUI): Companion (pp. 27-28).

DOI: https://doi.org/10.1145/3308557.3308685

Gelsomini M., Cosentino G., Spitale M., **Gianotti M**., Fisicaro D., Leonardi G., Riccardi F., Piselli A., Beccaluva E., Bonadies B., Di Terlizzi L., Zinzone M., Alberti S., Rebourg C., Carulli M., Garzotto F., Arquilla V., Bisson M., Del Curto B., Bordegoni M. (2019, May). **Magika, a multisensory environment for play, education and inclusion**. In Extended abstracts of the 2019 ACM CHI conference on human factors in computing systems (pp. 1-6).

DOI: https://doi.org/10.1145/3290607.3312753

Cosentino G., **Gianotti M**., Gelsomini M., Garzotto F., Arquilla V. (2019 June) **Environment fostering children's well being** – In Proceedings of the 3rd International Conference on Environmental Design 2019, published Mediterranean Design Association (MDA) (pp. 305-312). (No. 1376).

URL: https://www.easychair.org/publications/preprint download/KWXV

Crovari, P., **Gianotti, M.**, Riccardi, F., & Garzotto, F. (2019, September). **Designing a smart toy: guidelines from the experience with smart dolphin" SAM"**. In Proceedings of the 13th ACM Biannual Conference of the Italian SIGCHI Chapter: Designing the next interaction (CHIItaly) (pp. 1-10).

DOI: https://doi.org/10.1145/3351995.3352041

2020

Gianotti, M., Riccardi, F., Cosentino, G., Garzotto, F., & Matera, M. (2020, October). Modeling interactive smart spaces. In Conceptual Modeling: 39th International Conference, ER 2020, Vienna, Austria, November 3–6, 2020, Proceedings (pp. 403-417). Cham: Springer International Publishing.

DOI: https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-62522-1_30

Garzotto, F., Beccaluva, E., **Gianotti, M.**, & Riccardi, F. (2020, April). **Interactive multisensory environments for primary school children**. In Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (pp. 1-12).

DOI: https://doi.org/10.1145/3313831.337634

Cosentino, G., **Gianotti, M.**, Riccardi, F., & Garzotto, F. (2020, June). **Empowering caregivers in multisensory smart spaces for education and therapy**. In Workshop EMPATHY at ACM International Conference on Advanced Visual Interfaces (AVI), ACM (pp. 31-36).

URL: http://ceur-ws.org/Vol-2702/EMPATHY_2020_paper_6.pdf

Gianotti, M., Riccardi, F., Cosentino, G., Garzotto, F., & Matera, M. (2020 June). Conceptual Modeling of Multisensory Smart Spaces. In Workshop EMPATHY at ACM International Conference on Advanced Visual Interfaces (AVI), ACM (pp. 25-30).

URL: https://ceur-ws.org/Vol-2702/EMPATHY 2020 paper 5.pdf

2022

Vona, F., **Gianotti, M.**, Patti, A., Barbieri, J., Moskwa, L., Di Gioia, F. R., & Garzotto, F. (2022 June). **Improving the daily autonomy of people with Autism Spectrum Disorder through Virtual and Augmented Reality.** In Workshop Enhancing Cross-Reality applications and user experiences at ACM International Conference on Advanced Visual Interfaces (AVI)

URL: https://cr-workshop.github.io/papers/vona2022-improving.pdf

Vona, F., **Gianotti, M.**, Patti, A., Barbieri, J., Moskwa, L., Di Gioia, F. R., & Garzotto, F. (2022, June). **Combining Virtual and Augmented Reality to improve daily autonomy for people with Autism Spectrum Disorder**. In Proceedings of the 2022 ACM International Conference on Advanced Visual Interfaces (AVI) (pp. 1-3).

DOI: https://doi.org/10.1145/3531073.3534499

Beccaluva, E., Riccardi, F., **Gianotti, M.**, Barbieri, J., & Garzotto, F. (2022). **VIC—A Tangible User Interface to train memory skills in children with Intellectual Disability.** International Journal of Child-Computer Interaction, 32, (pp. 1-13).

DOI: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijcci.2021.100376

Giudici, M., Beccaluva, E., **Gianotti, M.,** Barbieri, J., Caslini, G., & Garzotto, F. (2022, June). **A Pilot Study on Interactive Multisensory Environments for Neuropsychological Assessment**. In Proceedings of the 2022 ACM International Conference on Advanced Visual Interfaces (pp. 1-5).

DOI: https://doi.org/10.1145/3531073.3531169

Ghiazzi, S., Riva, S., **Gianotti, M**., Crovari, P., & Garzotto, F. (2022, June). **MagicMuseum: Team-based Experiences in Interactive Smart Spaces for Cultural Heritage Education**. In Proceedings of the 2022 International Conference on Advanced Visual Interfaces (pp. 1-3).

DOI: https://doi.org/10.1145/3531073.3534488

Komarova, S., **Gianotti, M**., Atanassov, A., Bordonaro, G., Rousseau, C., Goldschmidt, M., ... & Garzotto, F. (2022, June). **Investigation and perspectives about the promoting creativity to children with ASD in a Multisensory environment Magic Room. Generative game "Explora!".** In International Conference EdMedia+ Innovate Learning (pp. 696-710). Association for the Advancement of Computing in Education (AACE).

URL: https://www.learntechlib.org/p/221360/

2023

Secco M., **Gianotti M.**, Garzotto F., Colombo A. (2023, August). **Multisensory Climbing in the Magic Room**. In Proceedings of IFIP 2023 International Conference Interact.

DOI: https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-42293-5_68

Gianotti M., Patti A., Vona F., Pentimalli F., Barbieri J., Garzotto F. (2023 July). **Multimodal Interaction for Persons with Autism: The 5A Case Study**. In Proceedings of HCI INTERNATIONAL 2023 25th International Conference on Human-Computer Interaction, Cham: Springer International Publishing.

DOI: https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-35681-0_38

PARTICIPATION AND MANAGEMENT OF NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL RESEARCH PROJECTS_

MANAGEMENT OF INTERNATIONAL RESEARCH PROJECTS

JANUARY INCLUDE - AI ENHANCED MOBILE SOLUTIONS FOR CHARITIES

- DECEMBER 2022 PERIOD TIME OF THE PROJECT: JANUARY-DECEMBER 2022

Role: WP leader "A2202: Technical Solution/MVP"

Funding Institution: EC

Funding Program: EIT Digital

JANUARY SARA++ - SMART SOCIAL ROBOTS FOR THE ELDERLY

- DECEMBER 2021 PERIOD TIME OF THE PROJECT: JANUARY-DECEMBER 2021

Role: WP Leader "A2102: Technical Solution/MVP"

Funding Institution: EC

Funding Program: EIT Digital

JANUARY PLET - PROJECT LIFE MANAGEMENT FOR E- TOYS #18085-2018

- DECEMBER 2018 PERIOD TIME OF THE PROJECT: JANUARY-DECEMBER 2018

Role: WP Leader "WP A1804 - Gateway and Data acquisition from e-toys"

Funding Institution: **EC**

Funding Program: EIT Digital

MANAGEMENT OF NATIONAL RESEARCH PROJECTS

DECEMBER 2022 ACTIVE3 - EVERYONE, EVERYWHERE, EVERYDAY

- PRESENT PERIOD TIME OF THE PROJECT: OCTOBER 2022-SEPTEMBER 2024

Role: Task Leader WP3 "Platform for inclusion"/Task 1: . Multisensory Spaces

Funding Institution: Fondazione Cariplo and Regione Lombardia

Funding Program: Emblematic Program

JANUARY 2022 5A - AUTONOMIE PER L'AUTISMO ATTRAVERSO REALTÀ VIRTUALE, - MARCH 2023 REALTÀ AUMENTATA, E AGENTI CONVERSAZIONALI

PERIOD TIME OF THE PROJECT: MARCH 2021-MARCH 2023

Role: WP Leader "WP3: Development of prototype 1"; "WP5: Development of prototype 2"; "WP7:

Engineering

Funding Institution: TIM Foundation

Funding Program: Programma TIM "Liberi di Comunicare"

MATTIA GIANOTTI_CV

PARTICIPATION IN NATIONAL RESEARCH PROJECTS

DECEMBER 2022 NEXT GENERATION UPP

- SEPTEMBER2023 PERIOD TIME OF THE PROJECT: SEPTEMBER 2022-SEPTEMBER 2023

Role: Participant "WP 1.3 Interface Development"

Funding Institution: Italian Ministry of Justice

Funding Program: PON- Governance e Capacità istituzionale – Asse I-Azione 1.4.1

NOVEMBER 2017 LUDOMI - SMART MULTISENSORY SPACES FOR CHILDREN WITH - FEBRUARY 2019 INTELLECTUAL DISABILITY

PERIOD TIME OF THE PROJECT: MARCH 2017-FEBRUARY 2019

Role: Participant "WP4: Smart Space Platform Development"

Funding Institution: **Politecnico di Milano** Funding Program: Polisocial Award 2017

6/9

MATTIA GIANOTTI_CV

CONFERENCES_

21/04/2018 **MONTREAL**

- 26/04/2018 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems

04/05/2019 **GLASGOW**

- 09/05/2019 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems

25/04/2020 **HONOLULU**

- 30/04/2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems

03/11/2020 **VIENNA**

- 06/11/2020 ER Conference International Conference on Conceptual Modeling

06/06/2022 FRASCATI, ROME

- 10/06/2022 AVI 2022 International Conference on Advanced Visual Interfaces

SPEAKER TO CONFERENCES_

03/11/2020 **VIENNA (ONLINE)**

Modeling interactive smart spaces. In Conceptual Modeling: 39th International Conference, ER 2020, Vienna, Austria, November 3–6, 2020, Proceedings (pp. 403-417). Cham: Springer International Publishing.

DOI: https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-62522-1 30

AWARDS_

- 06/11/2020

BEST POSTER AWARD

24th International Conference on Intelligent User Interfaces: Companion IUI 2019 Conference - GENIEL: an auto-generative intelligent interface to empower learning in a multi-sensory environment – DOI: https://doi.org/10.1145/3308557.3308685

MATTIA GIANOTTI CV

TEACHING EXPERIENCE_

AA 2023-2024 ADJUNCT PROFESSOR

Course: Final Design Studio - Technologies for Connected Products and Systems in master program for Digital and Interaction Design - Scuola del Design (3 CFU)

AA 2022-2023 ADJUNCT PROFESSOR

Course: Laboratorio di Computer Grafica – Modulo Informatica Applicata in Bachelor program for Design school (5 CFU)

AA 2020-2021 - PRESENT TEACHING ASSISTANT IN THE FOLLOWING MASTER PROGRAM COURSES IN COMMUNICATION DESIGN:

Applied Informatics (Prof. Franca Garzotto) - AA 2020-2021
Applied Informatics (Prof. Franca Garzotto) - AA 2021-2022
Applied Informatics (Prof. Franca Garzotto) - AA 2022-2023

AA 2017-2018 - PRESENT

TEACHING ASSISTANT IN THE FOLLOWING MASTER PROGRAM COURSES IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING:

Advanced User Interfaces (Prof. Franca Garzotto) - AA 2017-2018

Hypermedia Applications (Prof. Franca Garzotto) - AA 2017-2018

Advanced User Interfaces (Prof. Franca Garzotto) - AA 2018-2019

Hypermedia Applications (Prof. Franca Garzotto) - AA 2018-2019

Advanced User Interfaces (Prof. Franca Garzotto) - AA 2019-2020

Hypermedia Applications (Prof. Franca Garzotto) - AA 2020-2021

Advanced User Interfaces (Prof. Franca Garzotto) - AA 2020-2021

Hypermedia Applications (Prof. Franca Garzotto) - AA 2021-2022

Advanced User Interfaces (Prof. Franca Garzotto) - AA 2021-2022

Advanced User Interfaces (Prof. Franca Garzotto) - AA 2022-2023

Advanced User Interfaces (Prof. Franca Garzotto) - AA 2023-2024

AA 2023-2024 - PRESENT

TEACHING ASSISTANT IN THE FOLLOWING BACHELOR PROGRAM COURSES IN COMMUNICATION DESIGN:

Laboratorio di Computer Grafica – Modulo Informatica Applicata (Prof. Federico Reghenzani) - AA 2023-2024

Laboratorio di Computer Grafica – Modulo Disegno Digitale (Prof. Maresa Bertolo) - AA 2023-2024

MATTIA GIANOTTI CV

2018

- PRESENT

SUPERVISION OF MASTER THESIS

2018 Matteo Virtuani (Communication Design) - EOM System Elicitation of Olfactory Memory System. A new rehabilitation experience for children with NDD and ASD

2018 Andrea Paramithiotti (Computer Science and Engineering) - GENPLAY: GENERATIVE PLAYSCAPE

2021 Mattia Bacarella, Diego Costanzelli (Computer Science and Engineering) - LiTouch: Smart Interface for User Interaction on Large Screens

2021 Eva Baldasseroni, Giacomo Caslini (Computer Science and Engineering) - Coding Experiences for Children in an Interactive Smart Space

2021 Mathyas Giudici (Computer Science and Engineering) - BrainTraining: a suite of neuropsychological games in the Magic Room

2021 Andrea Rotella (Biomedical Engineering) - Engineering human connections in the Magic Room: from emotion recognition to affective synchronies visualization

2021 Simone Ghiazzi, Stefano Riva (Computer Science and Engineering) – Magic Museum: a Team based Interactive Customizable Museum Experience in Interactive Smart Spaces

2022 Leonardo Guerra, Martino Manzolini (Computer Science and Engineering) – Improving the daily autonomy of autistic person in urban mobility through Augmented Reality and Conversational Agents

2022 Clarence Antichi, Federico Alterio (Computer Science and Engineering) – Oceania: exploring social interactions and creativity through a multisensory environment game application

2023 Caterina Merendi (Design and Engineering) – From PeekABook to Storiello A Storytelling journey

2023 Sara Cardettini (Design and Engineering) – *PeekABook and Beyond: Interactive Storytelling with Minimito*

RESEARCH PERIOD ABROAD_

03/12/2019 - 12/03/2020

UNIVERSITAT POMPEU FABRA - BARCELONA

I spent 4 months at Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF) under the supervision of prof **Narcis Pares** at European Media and Immersion **Lab EMIL** (https://emil-xr.eu/)

At UPF I have worked on evolution of the notorious project **Lands of Fog** to create an engaging, open ended cooperative exploratory experience called **Spark** based on a generative approach in response to autistic users cooperative behaviors. Within our studies we have measured promising results in supporting social skills development to a larger extend than Lands of Fog, both in terms of efficacy and longer exposure interest. Study was unfortunately interrupted by Covid-19 outbreak. The planned period abroad was of 8 months, however due to Covid-19 pandemic, it has to be interrupted earlier than the predefined time.

PERSONAL DATA_

I hereby authorize the use of my personal data in accordance to the GDPR 679/16 - "European regulation on the protection of personal data".

Autorizzo al trattamento dati ai sensi del GDPR 2016/679 del 27 aprile 2016 (Regolamento Europeo relativo alla protezione delle persone fisiche per quanto riguarda il trattamento dei dati personali).

Autorizzo la pubblicazione del Curriculum Vitae sul sito istituzionale del Politecnico di Milano (sez. Amministrazione Trasparente) in ottemperanza al D. Lgs n. 33 del 14 marzo 2013 (e s.m.i.).